בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is סמך Samech 60, and
we start literally at the top of the page. And the issue
here was that the משנה Mishnah said that after the bloods, not
just of what you spill at the base of the altar for
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the outer altar on the west side, the
side you hit when you come out, but also the normal קרבנות
korbanot that you spill the remainder of the blood on the south
side, it says that all the bloods sort of come together and
go out into through the channel, through the ditch, and they it
empties into נחל קידרון, Nachal Kidron, the wadi of Kidron, and there
it is sold for fertilizer, but before sold, the selling actually, the
paying of the money redeems its קדושה kedusha onto the money. But
so before that there still is a problem of מעילה. me'ilah.
Now that would seem to be only a rabbinic מעילה me'ilah because
the מצוה mitzvah was already done. But the גמרא Gemara makes an
even bolder statement that says that there's no מעילה me'ilah on blood
used for קרבנות korbanot even before the מצוה mitzvah is done, even
though it's sanctified, it's all being put on the מזבח, mizbeach, it's
and so on, and it quotes three פסוקים. pesukim. One is נתתי
לכם, natati lachem, it's for your purposes, or לכפר, lechaper, it's for
כפרה, kapara, not for מעילה, me'ilah, as we pointed out the part
of the significance there is is that it is not something offered
to God like the like the meat and like the limbs and
so on, it is something that is put on the מזבח, mizbeach,
it effectuates כפרה, kapara, but it's not an offering.
And then what the גמרא Gemara focused on was this issue that
it is the word of הוא, hu, כי הדם הוא, ki hadam
hu, at the same way after atonement there's no מעילה me'ilah because
the מצוה mitzvah is done, then the same is true before atonement
as opposed to other things where until the מצוה mitzvah is done
there is מעילה, me'ilah, here there is no מעילה me'ilah before because
there is no מעילה me'ilah after. And now the גמרא Gemara is
asking the question about how do you know that's the rule, maybe
the rule should be that it remains the same and there's מעילה
me'ilah both before and after, rather than neither before and after. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, we would not have it, we would
not have מעילה me'ilah in something after the מצוה mitzvah is done
because we know that that never happens except in like one or
two exceptions and those exceptions prove that those are what we call
the exceptions that prove the rule, prove that the rule is is
that is that is that normally there is no מעילה me'ilah after
the מצוה mitzvah is done and therefore that has to be the
case by the blood. And if that's true after, it's going to
be true before as well. Let me just read one line then
I'll take the question. So let's just read the top line of
דף daf to reorient ourselves. משום דהוי mishum de'havay תרומת הדשן trumat
hadeshen ובגדי כהונה u'vigdei kehuna שני כתובים הבאים
כאחד. shenei kesuvim habayim ke'echad. אי Ay we learn that from תרומת
הדשן, trumat hadeshen, the ashes that are put on the side of
the altar every single morning, not when you really clean the altar
but more the ritual placing of the ashes, you cannot get benefit
after the ashes are put there, and the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna
from the כהן גדול kohen gadol after he wears it on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, you can't use it afterwards, and we learn from
there that also cannot be used even after the מצוה mitzvah is
done. So those two are the exceptions. וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד
אין מלמדין. v'chol shenei kesuvim habayim ke'echad ein melamdin. Anytime you have
two exceptions, one exception maybe the exception is the rule, but there's
two exceptions, two exceptions prove the opposite rule, prove that these are
the exceptions, the other is the rule. So the rule is is
that everything else therefore after the מצוה mitzvah is done there is
not a problem and that has to be true by the blood
and if it's true after it's done it's not a it's not
a problem it's true even before. And just to remind us what
I pointed out yesterday, a very large תוספות Tosfos that says it's
not necessarily true that there's מעילה me'ilah by the תרומת הדשן trumat
hadeshen after the מצוה mitzvah is done. רש"י Rashi says since it's
forbidden in benefit we can infer that it still has the קדושה
kedusha and we can infer that there's מעילה. me'ilah. תוספות Tosfos says
no, not necessarily, but it is אסור assur after the מצוה mitzvah
is done and that's enough of an exception to prove that the
rule is that after the מצוה mitzvah is done by everything else,
you know, the status goes away, but not necessarily that it's מעילה,
me'ilah, but that it does remain it is אסור assur after the
מצוה mitzvah and again that is an exception. Yes, Charlie.
By the the issue of it's for you in terms of atonement,
not all of the קרבנות korbanot are described as having an atonement,
some are
are for רצון.
ratzon. Yeah,
it's true but when the תורה Torah talks about the role of
blood it doesn't distinguish the blood of which קרבנות. korbanot. It says
don't eat blood because I've given the blood to you on מזבח
mizbeach לכפר. lechaper. So
it's it is an interesting question and it is worth raising that
issue like in the context of יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well,
how much is כפרה, kapara, you know, seen as the as something
that covers all, you know, everything. Like the גמרא Gemara has to
prove that the קטורת ketoret was מכפר, mechaper, but it could have
accepted that that, you know, you well, the question is before it
proves it or after. Before it could have accepted the possibility that
there are things that are done that are not כפרה kapara oriented.
I don't think anybody thinks that the מנורה menorah or the שולחן,
shulchan, you know, the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim is מכפר. mechaper. But
in terms of קרבנות, korbanot, you know, do we think that the
blood... blood of the קרבנות korbanot and the use of the blood,
that that always has a כפרה kapparah component regardless of the, of
what the more dominant theme of the קרבן korban is? I think
that that's a very important question. But the פסוקים psukim that talk
about דם dam just treat it all as לכפר. lechaper. Yes.
I'm sorry. How is it that only one exception could be the
rule? I thought we usually say an exception that proves the rule.
Yeah. No. So so there's a principle, if you don't know what
the rule is and you're told that this is the הלכה halacha
here, right, so that might be a בנין אב. binyan av. בנין
אב binyan av is a paradigm. You're told the הלכה, halacha, that
should tell you that that everything is like this. Okay. So I
mean if you now maybe you start with an assumption that it's
an exception because there's something you would have sort of logically figured
out would have made the rule otherwise or somehow you had another
basis for something else being the rule, then you wouldn't say,
so that gets a little bit more fuzzy. But if you just
start with the one case, then you sort of say that might
be the rule. Right. Two cases already if the rule was, if
that was the rule, it wouldn't have had to say it twice.
All right. So let's read a little bit more, let's get a
little bit further. So גמרא Gemara says הניחא לרבנן דאמרי והניחם שם
מלמד שטעונים גניזה. hani nicha lerabanan de'amri vehiniacham sham melamed shete'unim genizah.
Fine. I can I can concede you have two exceptions according to
the rabbis that say that you should place them by the בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehunah of יום כיפור Yom Kippur means that you can't
use it afterwards. אלא לרבי דוסא דאמר בגדי כהונה ראויים הם לכהן
הדיוט, Ella lerabbi Dosa de'amar bigdei kehunah re'uyim heim lekohen hedyot, and
according to Rabbi Dosa who says that you could use the בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehunah afterwards. Interestingly not that you can use it again
for a for another יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but a normal כהן
kohen could use it because the white בגדים begadim are the same.
So according to him and as Rashi points out at the time,
it's a little bit ironic, you would have thought that's going down
in קדושה, kedushah, but apparently for him the bigger issue is the
uniqueness of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So each יום כיפור Yom Kippur
needs its own בגדים begadim and therefore don't use it for another
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but you can go ahead and another כהן
kohen can use it. So it's not an exception. You don't see
an example that the מצוה mitzvah is done and it still remains
prohibited. The מצוה mitzvah isn't done by this. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? So משום דהוי תרומת הדשן
ועגלה ערופה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. mishum dehavyi terumat hadeshen ve'eglah arufah
shenei ketuvim habaim ke'echad. No, there's another case that's an exception that
the מצוה mitzvah is done and it's still a problem, and that's
עגלה ערופה. eglah arufah. After you break the neck, it's forbidden בהנאה.
behana'ah. Okay. וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. vechol shenei ketuvim
habaim ke'echad ein melamdin. And therefore two things that the מצוה mitzvah
is done and you cannot learn it out. Again, does it mean
that עגלה ערופה eglah arufah is מעילה me'ilah or does it just
mean אסור בהנאה? assur behana'ah? Not clear. רש"י Rashi is reading the
גמרא Gemara literally as מעילה, me'ilah, תוספות Tosafot is willing to accept
that some of these cases is only איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. But
nevertheless, it's an example that there are some cases that remain problematic
afterwards, which would mean that other things do not remain problematic afterwards.
What do you mean other, like the עגלה ערופה? eglah arufah?
Yeah, he's already has two, then he needs a third
for?
Yeah, because it's an exception.
No, but you already had two exceptions.
No, but you need to tell me that this is also an
exception, otherwise I would have said the הלכה halacha by the עגלה
ערופה eglah arufah would have been the rule.
No, we rejected בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehunah.
No, no, but he's saying if you if you accepted בגדי כהונה,
bigdei kehunah, you don't need עגלה ערופה eglah arufah to tell me
that it's an exception. You need עגלה ערופה eglah arufah to tell
me that, you don't need עגלה ערופה eglah arufah to tell me
what the rule is, you need to tell me about עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah because it is an exception. You need to tell me
it's an exception. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר
אין מלמדין. hani nicha leman de'amar ein melamdin.
Fine. That's good according to the one that says once you have
two exceptions you cannot learn out the general rule from that. אלא
למאן דאמר מלמדין, Ella leman de'amar melamdin, there's there's a position that
says even if it says it twice, maybe those are examples of
the rule and not exceptions. So what are you going to do?
So maybe the rule would be that everything even after it's done
remains forbidden in one way or another. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? So תרי מיעוטי כתיבי. terei mi'utei
ketivi. No, they're not just two exceptions, there's also two extra words
that say it only applies in this case that that it remains
problematic. ושמו, Vesamo, you shall place it, the the the ashes of
the תרומת הדשן. terumat hadeshen. So the ו, vav, it, not just
ושם, vesam, means this is a rule that applies only to it.
והערופה, Veha'arufah,
the one with the broken neck, so only this is a one
that this rule applies to. So those extra מיעוטים, mi'utim, that's now
we're up to four because you have the two cases that are
exceptions plus two מיעוטים, mi'utim, should give you like four things. So
those we'll try to figure out why you needed all of those.
But anyway, the point is even if normally you need three exceptions,
here you have two exceptions plus extra letters that say it's unique
to these cases, which means these are the exceptions and the rule
is not this rule is the other one.
So what is the case of עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah that we're trying to say? That it remains forbidden even
after the neck is broken, even after the מצוה mitzvah is done.
Is done. So it's a case where, so these are cases that
remain forbidden after the מצוה mitzvah is done, they are the exceptions.
The rule is everything else is permissible. Therefore we would have assumed
blood would be permissible after the מצוה mitzvah is done, and once
it's permissible after the מצוה mitzvah is done because of the פסוק
pasuk of הוא, hu, we say it's permissible even before. So again,
it's just a third approach to learn out why blood is how
we know blood of קרבנות korbanot is not, not לכתחילה, lechatchila, obviously
there's a דרבנן derabbanan מעילה, me'ilah, that's what the משנה Mishnah says,
there's מעילה me'ilah even after the מצוה mitzvah rabbinically. Okay biblically there's
no מעילה meilah even before
the מצוה's mitzvah done. Right the exceptions are and whether it's מעילה
meilah is not clear but at least it's עגלה ערופה eglah arufah
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen those might those are
the exceptions.
But it's a good thing then I guess by נחל איתן nachal
eitan you're gonna come in.
Exactly. Okay so now the גמרא gemara says והני תלת קראי
בדם למה לי? v'hanai tlas krai b'dam lama li? Okay so good.
So now we know our משנה mishnah tells us that there's an
איסור מעילה issur meilah even after the מצוה's mitzvah done that's דרבנן
derabanan and therefore if you want to use it for fertilizer you
have to pay for it and the קדושה kedushah gets transferred to
the money that's דרבנן. derabanan. Biblically there's no מעילה meilah even before
the מצוה's mitzvah done. Now since we're talking about blood we say
why did there need to be three פסוקים psukim by blood? What's
the three פסוקים? psukim? So it's you know so it says לכם
lachem לכפר l'chaper and והוא. hoo. Okay cause we sort of said
that you know we had three good ways to learn out that
there's no מעילה. meilah.
So why do we need all so rather so you know even
if you're if you're the אמורא amora that picked way number one
there's also two and three. So what are all the what are
the three words doing? Why you know according cause everybody picked one
of three legitimate words to learn it out from. So why do
you need all three? So the גמרא gemara says חד למיעוטי מנותר
chad l'miutei mi'nosar one to tell you so not only is blood
not מעילה meilah we're going to find out that blood is excluded
blood of קרבנות korbanot from a lot of other prohibitions that normally
apply to קרבנות. korbanot. Let's say you left the blood over and
you didn't put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and it's you know
and it's נותר. nosar. So or you know or the שיירים shirayim
you left over maybe you sprinkled the blood you left the שיירים
shirayim over now you ate the blood. So you get כרת kares
for eating blood but you would not get כרת kares for eating
נותר. nosar. And it's not just because you can't get double you
know punished twice. רש״י Rashi says even if let's say you were
שוגג shogeg for the blood the איסור issur of blood and מזיד
mezid for the איסור issur of נותר nosar you would get no
punishment for the איסור issur of נותר nosar okay because נותר nosar
does not apply by blood. So it's sort of like לכם lachem
it's yours again and we're freeing it from the normal thank you
restrict the normal astringencies of קרבנות korbanot quite a shocking idea. That's
so to exclude from נותר nosar וחד למיעוטי ממעילה v'chad l'miutei mi'meilah
one is as we already said to exclude from מעילה meilah וחד
למיעוטי מטומאה v'chad l'miutei mi'tumah from טומאה tumah which doesn't mean it
doesn't become טמא tamei but which means that even if you're טמא
tamei and you eat blood that you are do not do the
transgression of eating קרבן korban when you are טמא. tamei. So the
three פסוקים psukim the גמרא's gemara saying is not that everybody agrees
that each one of those words says says blood is special blood
does not have you know is not treated like a normal קרבן
korban it's לכם lachem as it were or לכפר l'chaper it's only
there for you only there to atone and therefore it's excluded from
not just מעילה meilah but from other restrictions of קרבנות korbanot from
נותר nosar from eating it בטומאה b'tumah and so on. Now I
should say that
well you know let's just finish the משנה mishnah and then I'll
make my comment. The גמרא gemara says אבל מפיגול aval mi'pigul now
somebody might somebody might go your I was you know if you'd
be on the ball we're waiting for you to yell out. You
saw that word. Oh that's great. You have נותר nosar טומאה tumah
מעילה meilah how about the other classic prohibition by קרבן korban פיגול?
pigul? If you have the wrong thoughts for the wrong time you
know then the whole קרבן korban becomes אסור asur and there's an
איסור כרת. issur kares. So let's say you had a פיגול pigul
thought by a קרבן korban and you ate the blood. You made
it פיגול. pigul. If you eat the meat now you're חייב כרת.
chayav kares. What happens if you eat the blood? You're also don't
get כרת kares you're also off the hook. So all of the
restrictions of קרבנות korbanot פיגול pigul נותר nosar טומאה tumah מעילה meilah
don't apply by blood. Now why don't you need a פסוק pasuk
to exclude פיגול? pigul? How do you know to exclude it? לא
צריך למיעוטי קרא. lo tzarich l'miutei kra. You don't need a פסוק
pasuk to exclude. דתנן d'nan because we have a rule that naturally
excludes the blood. What's the rule? כל שיש לו מתירין בין לאדם
בין למזבח חייבין עליו משום פיגול. kol sheyesh lo matirin bein l'adam
bein l'mizbe'ach hayavin alav mishum pigul.
Anything that you that some other thing makes it
permissible that it's if B becomes permissible because you did something with
something else with A then there could be פיגול pigul by B.
So normally that's true about you know the meat becomes permissible to
eat because you did the זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. The אימורים emurim
become permissible on the מזבח mizbe'ach because you did the you know
because you did the זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. The שיירים shirayim of
a מנחה mincha become permissible because you did the קומץ. kometz. So
any so the thing that became permissible because you did something else
that has the הלכה halachah of פיגול. pigul. והדם עצמו מתיר הוא.
v'hadam atzmo matir hu. But the blood the blood isn't a B
the blood is the A. The blood is the thing you put
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. There's nothing that makes the blood now changes
its state to allow it to be eaten or to allow it
to go on the altar. So פיגול pigul doesn't apply to the
מתיר matir פיגול pigul applies to the thing that is becoming permissible
as a result. And רש״י Rashi shows the פסוקים psukim where we
learn that from. So okay there's an anyway a technical reason that
blood is excluded but more powerfully blood is excluded from all of
these and I have to say that that's you know even a
bigger חידוש hiddush than yesterday.
Right. So it's one thing to say there's no מעילה, Me'ilah, because
as I said to you already, the exception of מעילה, Me'ilah, there
could be things that are, that have קדושה, Kedushah, but there's no
מעילה Me'ilah because it's not קדשי השם, Kadshei Hashem, it's not מיוחד
Meyuchad to God. So again, still ironic, you would have said if
anything is מיוחד Meyuchad to God, it's the blood, but I think
that's the power of the פסוקים: Pesukim: לכם, Lachem, לכפר. Lekaper. It's
not being offered to God. It's put on the מזבח Mizbe'ach and
effects כפרה, Kapparah, but it's not being offered to God. Fine. So
מעילה Me'ilah anyway is a narrow category. The same way פיגול, Pigul,
there are technical issues that exclude it. But the idea of נותר
Nosar and טמא, Tamei, right, that would just be the קדושה Kedushah
itself should make that a problem and you know even you know
why is it that it gets excluded? So there's a real power
to this idea of לכם Lachem or לכפר Lekaper that the whole
idea of the blood is there for your sake and therefore not
to trip you up. But again,
it's a strange idea, I'm having a hard time getting my head
around it about conceptually what that says about the role that blood
plays here. It's somehow out of the normal קרבן Korban role and
maybe that gets to the idea of the גמרא Gemara at the
end about מתיר הוא. Matir Hu. You know, since it's the מתיר,
matir, it's the thing that is doing the קרבן, Korban, somehow all
the הלכות Halachot of the
קרבן Korban apply to sort of what's left over, not to the
thing that actually represents the very essence of the קרבן Korban itself.
But again, it's quite ironic, I really can't fully explain it. All
right, now we move on. So that was a fascinating little digression
about דם. Dam. That could have been a סוגיא Sugya straight out
of זבחים. Zevachim. Okay, but now we get back to. So the
blood was poured at the base of the altar. We discussed in
general, blood at the base of the altar. Again, we're always sort
of pulling back a little bit and giving it a larger context.
So we discussed the מעילה Me'ilah that applies by blood. And now
what have we done? We
have now basically gone through the entire עבודה Avodah till the end
of the inner עבודה, Avodah, right? What are the stuff that are
done with בגדי לבן Bigdei Lavan on? Right? He only wears the
white garments twice. Right? The second time he, it's just to take
out the מחתה, Mahtah, the fire pan. So the first time where
he's doing all of the stuff with the בגדי לבן Bigdei Lavan
on, what does he do? He does the קטורת, Ketoret, he does
the blood of the, you know, of the
פר, Par, and then he does the blood of the שעיר. Se'ir.
Now it is true, the one big thing that we haven't done
yet is we've done אחת ואחת, Achat ve-Achat, right, and then we
didn't do it, but you know the thing that we do, how
you כורעים ומשתחווים Kor'im u-Mishtachavim when he said, you know, חטאתי, Chatati,
you know, כי ביום הזה יכפר עליכם. Ki Vayom Hazeh Yechaper Aleichem.
So what but what's the one big thing of the עבודה Avodah
we haven't gotten to?
The שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir la-Azazel. Okay, so we're going to get to
that. But that's not inside the היכל, Heichal, that's in the עזרה.
Azarah. He does a וידוי Viduy and it gets sent off. And
then it's going to be exciting to discuss how it gets sent
off and goes over the cliff. But basically, in terms of his
עבודה Avodah inside, right, you know, even the פסוקים Pesukim sort of
acknowledge, even the פסוקים Pesukim underscore, you know, sort of that this
now completes major like major step, right? Because it says, I'll read,
the פסוקים Pesukim are, right, וכלה מכפר את הקדש, Vechilah mi-kaper et
ha-Kodesh, וחטא הקדש, Vechiteh ha-Kodesh, כאשר עשה לדם הפר, ka-asher asah le-dam
ha-par, והזה עליו מן הדם באצבעו שבע פעמים, ve-hizah alav min ha-dam
be-etzba'o sheva pe'amim, וכלה מכפר את הקדש. Vechilah mi-kaper et ha-kodesh. So
that's the פרוכת. Parochet. וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד ve-chol adam
lo yiyeh be-Ohel Moed בבאו לכפר בקדש עד צאתו, be-vo'o le-chaper ba-kodesh
ad tzeito, וכפר בעדו ובעד ביתו וכל קהל ישראל. ve-chiper ba-ado u-ve-ad
beito ve-chol kehal Yisrael. ויצא אל המזבח אשר לפני ה' וכפר עליו,
ve-yatza el ha-mizbe'ach asher lifnei Hashem ve-chiper alav, so even before he
gets to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it sounds like just
the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and the פרוכת Parochet achieved a major
level of כפרה Kapparah already at that stage, right? So that's important
to note: וכיפר על הקדש ve-chiper al ha-Kodesh מכל חטאותם, mi-kol chatotam,
וכל אדם, ve-chol adam, לכפר בקדש. lechaper ba-Kodesh. So even just the
קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and the פרוכת Parochet already the פסוקים Pesukim
are underscoring that is מכפר על הקדש. mechaper al ha-Kodesh. That's major
step number one. And then it says, ויצא אל המזבח אשר לפני
ה' וכפר עליו, ve-yatza el ha-mizbe'ach asher lifnei Hashem ve-chiper alav, ולקח
מדם הפר ומדם השעיר ונתן על קרנות המזבח סביב, ve-lakach mi-dam ha-par
u-mi-dam ha-se'ir ve-natan al קרנות המזבח סביב karnot ha-mizbe'ach saviv, so we
just discussed that, והזה עליו מן הדם באצבעו שבע פעמים וטהרו וקדשו
מטמאת בני ישראל. ve-hizah alav min ha-dam be-etzba'o sheva pe'amim ve-tiharo ve-kidesho
mi-tum'ot benei Yisrael. וכלה מכפר את הקדש ואת אהל מועד ואת המזבח
והקריב את השעיר החי. Vechilah mi-kaper et ha-Kodesh ve-et Ohel Moed ve-et
ha-Mizbe'ach ve-hikriv et ha-sa'ir he-chai. So here, וכלה מכפר את הקדש Vechilah
mi-kaper et ha-Kodesh was קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and the פרוכת. Parochet.
Then he went and he did the וכן יעשה לאהל מועד ve-chen
ya'aseh le-Ohel Moed is the פרוכת, Parochet, and then he was did
it on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So that's וכלה מכפר את הקדש ve-chilah
mi-kaper et ha-Kodesh which is קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, ואת אהל מועד
ve-et Ohel Moed which is the פרוכת, Parochet, right, ואת המזבח. ve-et
ha-Mizbe'ach. Those are the three components,
right? והקריב את השעיר החי. Ve-hikriv et ha-se'ir he-chai. וכלה, Vechila, he's
done. So we have now reached the end of just at the
end of major stage number one. And now it's going to be
a different discussion about the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir la-Azazel. But we should
realize, you know, again in terms of the פסוקים, Pesukim, the big
underscore that you're done and you've done what you needed to do
etc. is all here by, it's all here by after he's done
with
the עזרה Azarah and the
היכל. Heichal.
Right, so anyway, so here you go, let's recreate it for ourselves.
So he did here, what was the order, right? So first he
does the קטורת, Ktores,
right? He does קטורת, Ktores, he burns קטורת, Ktores, then he gets
the, well first he does the שחיטת הפר, Shechitas Hapar, right? We're
going to, I'm going to number this because this is going to
become significant, right? Then somebody is stirring it, right?
Guy is stirring it the whole time, right?
The פר's par blood
or
whatever. Okay, so number one he does the שחיטת הפר Shechitas Hapar
and he does it in the north. So I got that out.
Okay anyway, he does the שחיטת הפר, Shechitas Hapar, then he comes
in and he does the קטורת, Ktores, okay, then he gets the
blood, so דם הפר, Dam Hapar,
then he שחט shechts the
שעיר, se'ir,
right? Then he does דם השעיר. Dam Hase'ir.
Yes, everybody with me? Okay, then out here by this he does
number six is דם הפר, Dam Hapar,
seven is דם השעיר, Dam Hase'ir, now on the פרוכת paroches here,
right? דם הפרוכת, Dam ha-paroches, right? Then he comes to the מזבח
mizbeach
and he does the, well he mixes them together, let's go like
our משנה, mishna, he already mixes them by the קרנות. kranos. So
he does פר ושעיר. Par ve-Se'ir.
Either walking or leaning. Exactly. Okay, he does the whole thing. וכילה
מכפר את הקודש, U-chila mi-kaper es ha-kodesh, right? This is הקודש, ha-kodesh,
this is אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, okay, and this is אהל מועד,
Ohel Moed, and this is as it were, this is the מזבח.
mizbeach. So look at those פסוקים pesukim again and you will see
how it emphasizes like you know he's done and certainly like you
know this is a major emphasis about this he's achieved the כפרה.
kaparah. And then it and then you know it's this and this
and then it says he finished everything. And now we're ready for
what's going to be the שעיר לעזאזל. se'ir la-azazel. Wait, I don't
understand number three. דם הפר. Dam Hapar. First he does the קטורת,
Ktores, שחט shechts the פר, par, does the
קטורת, Ktores, he brings the קטורת Ktores and the דם dam inside
at the same time?
No. No, he goes back out to get דם הפר, Dam Hapar,
but that's not, and goes back in. All right, fine. All right,
fine, so I can say that, I'll just put it here, I'll
just put it here sort of like 3A. You got to draw
the רביעי. revi'i. Get, yes, this is not precisely where it is,
it's over there. Fine, so we'll flip it over. Okay, 3A,
get דם הפר. Dam Hapar. This
this this. Okay, fine. All right. All right.
So now who's stirring? Can he like chat with his
buddies?
Possibly. I don't know. No, I don't think he, it's not an
עבודה. avodah. Okay, so now let's look at the משנה. mishna. כל
מעשה יום הכיפורים האמור על הסדר, Kol ma'aseh Yom HaKippurim ha-amur al
ha-seder, so the entirety of the entire order of יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, which has now been given an order, right, the סדר, seder,
אם
הקדים מעשה לחברו לא עשה כלום. im hikdim ma'aseh l'chavero lo asah
klum. If you put one, if you did one out of order,
you didn't do anything. So the one that you've done earlier, it's
not like it makes everything afterwards bad, it makes everything afterwards considered
also out of order. The only thing that's very important to underscore
that's considered out of order is the one that bumped in the
line. Right? Do you understand? You could have said that that makes
everything else also not good, because it makes everything else out of
order. But no, that's, that is the one that bumped the order,
that thing that you did early is no good.
But then you just do it
again in its right place.
And ignore everything else.
No, that's exactly my point. You only do that again. That is
no good, you ignore it, it's like nothing happened, and you'll do
it in its right place.
Right,
but back what it says חוק chok by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
so since חוק chok he'll לעכב. leakav. Yeah, it really has to
be done in the correct, no, but it's conceptually how do you
see it, meaning if you conceptually, that's what I'm underscoring, you know,
Michael saying well everything that comes after is also out of order,
it came after this. But once you say this is out of
order and this didn't count, so it didn't count, it makes it
that nothing else was out of order, because that what you did
was not the עבודה, avodah, was not the you know, it's only
out of order if you did an עבודה avodah that you know
beforehand. Okay. So the one you did earlier is no good. הקדים
דם השעיר לדם הפר, Hikdim dam hase'ir l'dam hapar,
so let's say you did the blood of the goat before the
blood of the ox, so the blood of the goat is was
out of order,
יחזור
ויזה מדם השעיר, yachzor v'yizeh midam hase'ir, the פר par is fine,
okay, and now and now do the שעיר se'ir again. Okay, לאחר
דם הפר, l'achar dam hapar, after you do the blood of the
פר, par, ואם עד שלא גמר את המתנות שבפנים נשפך הדם. v'im
ad shelo gamar es hamatanos shebifnim nishpach hadam.
Now, let's say you were sprinkling the blood inside, in the קדש
קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim. Okay, and you were אחת, אחת ואחת, אחת ושתים
achas, achas v'achas, achas v'shtayim and then you whoops, and you spilled
it all. Okay, so what do you have to do now? This
is not a, now this is like a different issue. This isn't
an out of order issue, this
is... Where do you pick off once something is interrupted? So it
says so in that case, so יביא גם אחר, Yavi gam acher,
bring other blood. Now, bring other blood does not mean you have
other blood stored up. It means שחט shacht another cow. Okay.
You don't have to שחט shacht another שעיר? sa'ir?
That is a very good question. Why if you're שחט shachting another
cow, don't you now have to שחט shacht another שעיר sa'ir and
get everything out back in order? Maybe you do. Okay, so Mike's
being on the ball, but that's not the focus right now of
the משנה. Mishna. The משנה's Mishna just saying where do you pick
up from? שחט Shacht another cow, שחט shacht another cow, get some
more blood, ויחזור בתחילה מבפנים, v'yachzor bitchila mibifnim, and pick up at
the beginning, meaning if even if you were one and six, go
back to the one. You know, go back to the beginning of
that עבודה. Avodah. If the עבודה Avodah is interrupted and you needed
another cow, go back to the beginning of the עבודה. Avodah. וכן
בהיכל. V'chein baHeichal. Now, similarly in the היכל, Heichal, if you were
doing, you know, you got to one and three on the פרוכת,
Paroches, and that got interrupted, get שחט shacht another cow, get more
blood and start with the one. But here's the חידוש. chiddush. What's
the חידוש? chiddush? If my היכל Heichal עבודה Avodah got interrupted, I'm
doing one, one and one, one and two, one and three, I
don't have to go back and do the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim,
right? You understand, you might say if you're getting new blood, you
gotta do everything about the blood from the beginning. The חידוש chiddush
is that each of these three things are considered independent: so the
only thing, the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, the פרוכת, Paroches, and the
מזבח. Mizbeach. So the only thing that you ruined as it were
was the one you were in the middle of. And that's the
only one you have to go back. What you've done, you've done,
that's sort of put away, you don't have to worry about that
anymore.
Stop, wait a minute, let's just finish. Okay. וכן בהיכל וכן במזבח.
V'chein baHeichal v'chein baMizbeach. Also by the מזבח, Mizbeach, if the blood
spilled, you שחט shacht another cow, you do the מזבח Mizbeach again,
but you do not have to go back to the קודש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim and the פרוכת. Paroches. מזבח הזהב. Mizbeach HaZahav. שכולם כפרה
בפני עצמן. Shekulam kapara bifnei atzman. It's very nice, it gives us
even a conceptual point. Each one is independent, so when you do
one, it's done, and you don't have to worry about going back
to it. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים ממקום שפסק משם הוא מתחיל.
Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon omrim mimakom shepasak misham hu matchil. They say
it's not even a problem to get blood of the cow, new
cow, and pick up in the middle. Right, you don't even have
to pick up at the beginning. If you were one and three,
שחט shacht a new cow and go on to one and four.
Okay. So if you might remember, that was discussed like earlier in
the גמרא Gemara as well, you know, because... because it's not the
same cow, you know, that the blood is sort of coming from,
but that's their חידוש chiddush that you can come in the middle.
Michael, you had a question.
What about the קטורת, ketores, which is somewhat of a כפרה kapara
but not the same way as דם? dam? I totally forgot the
קטורת. ketores.
Yeah, the קטורת ketores is part of this order.
That's why it's listed. So it means like this guy just totally
forgot it. So does he just go in, wait, and then do
I have to go back in and out again? Because like if
you didn't...
if you didn't do the קטורת ketores and you went straight to
the
דם dam and finished all the דם, dam, then right then bring
in the קטורת...
ketores... then bring it out... then everything that came before the קטורת
ketores is out of order and is no good. Because everything is
הקדים. hikdim. No, the next thing to do was the קטורת ketores
and you skipped it entirely. And you skipped it. So meaning that
everything now that you did is הקדים hikdim to the קטורת. ketores.
But that's a... that last position. No, meaning like the first one
is everything is...
this is not about out of order, this is about being interrupted.
Where do you pick up if you're interrupted?
אז אם הקדים לשלו לא עשה כלום. Az im hikdim leshelo lo
asah klum. Right.
So if you skipped the קטורת ketores and did other things, conceptually
what that means is all those other things are הקדים hikdim to
the קטורת. ketores. You're doing them before you did the קטורת, ketores,
which you should have done. So everything you're doing now, when you...
you know, if you... you gotta do everything all over again. Now,
the thing that the משנה Mishna does not address and is particularly,
you know, challenging because of the juxtaposition, is exactly this: one minute,
I get that you're saying once I'm done here, you know, if
I mess something up here, I don't have to worry about this,
I can just start again. But if I'm starting again here, I'm
שחט shachting a new cow, and that means if I'm שחט shachting
a new cow, two, three, four, everything here is out of order,
right? I'm שחט shachting a new cow and I'm going straight to
there. How does that work? Why isn't that like it's out of
order? Now, the חידוש chiddush might be it's not totally a new
cow, this you actually, you know, finished this, then that's been put
aside and, you know, even all the sort of order's been put
aside. But let's talk about the case that I spilled the blood
in here. Okay, if I spilled the blood in here, I was
up to number three, I spilled the blood of the פר, par,
I'm going to go back and שחט shacht the פר. par. Every...
the other things in here are... are also out of order, right?
I should... because one, two, three, four, and five are all connected
with the stuff that goes on inside. So if I spilled the
blood and have to go back to number one, how can I
not have to bring another קטורת, ketores, how can I not have
to שחט shacht another שעיר? sa'ir? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask that. But it's important, the first part of the
משנה Mishna only mentions the out of order, the second part the
interruption. But when you're talking about interrupting and then going and שחט
shachting another cow, then you have to ask the order question as
well. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. All right, our Rabbis taught: כל מעשי יום
הכיפורים. Kol ma'asei Yom HaKippurim. אמורים על הסדר, Amurim al HaSeder, everything
about יום כיפור Yom Kippur that's given an order. Now what's the
question interestingly is also האמור על הסדר. HaAmur al HaSeder. אמור Amur
by whom? אמור Amur by the Rabbis in the משנה Mishnah when
they describe the order, or might even mean just more black and
white, אמור Amur by the פסוקים, Psukim, right? The פסוקים Psukim are
the, the משנה Mishnah really very closely follow the פסוקים, Psukim, and
the order is very clear in the פסוקים. Psukim. So everything that
is given an order, אם הקדים מעשה לחברו לא עשה כלום. Im
hikdim ma'aseh lachaveiro lo asa klum. The thing that if you do
something early, the thing that, that jumped the line is, does not
count at all. אמר רבי יהודה אימתי? Amar Rabbi Yehuda Eimasai? When
is this true that there is a, that if you go out
of order, it didn't accomplish anything? בדברים הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבפנים. Bidvarim
hana'asim bevigdei lavan mifnim. Only the things that are done in the
white garments inside. Now that's pretty much everything except for שעיר לעזאזל,
Sa'ir LaAzazel, except that מבפנים mifnim does not mean the היכל. Heichal.
מבפנים Mifnim means קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says is the only place the order is critical is here,
things done in the white garments on the inside. After that, six,
seven, eight and on, if you, if you mess up the order,
it does not make it invalid. אינה מעכב. Einah me'akeiv. The thing
that you did out of order is fine. So if you went
ahead here and I don't know, you did the top of the
מזבח Mizbei'ach before you did the קרנות, Kranot, right? That would be
בדיעבד bedi'eved fine according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The thing you
did out of order doing
it for the...
what or if you did on the פרוכת, Parochet, you did the
דם השעיר Dam haSa'ir before the דם הפר? Dam haPar? Okay, the
only thing that's מעכב me'akeiv for him is the order inside of
there. Okay. But
this is only two things. Well, it's three: the קטורת, Ketoret, the
דם הפר, Dam haPar, and the דם השעיר. Dam haSa'ir. Okay.
So, but then
you wouldn't have to even check another פר Par there, right, if
you did it out of order you're fine, you're okay?
Except
unless you were in the מבפנים mifnim here, but out here wouldn't
be an issue, correct.
בדברים הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבפנים. Bidvarim hana'asim bevigdei lavan mifnim. אבל דברים
הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבחוץ, Aval d'varim hana'asim bevigdei lavan mibachutz, in the
outside, which merely means in the היכל, Heichal, not in the קודש
קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, אם הקדים מעשה לחברו מה שעשה עשוי. im hikdim
ma'aseh lachaveiro ma she'asa asuy. בדיעבד Bedi'eved it's okay if you go
out of order.
רבי נחמיה אומר במה דברים אמורים? Rabbi Nechemia omer Bameh devarim amurim?
בדברים הנעשים בבגדי לבן. Bidvarim hana'asim bevigdei lavan. No, no, no. The
order is critical in everything that you wear the white garments, meaning
everything in the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim and in the
עזרה. Azarah. Not עזרה, Azarah, excuse me, and in the
היכל. Heichal. בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ, Bein mifnim bein mibachutz, whether in
the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim or in the
היכל. Heichal. אבל דברים הנעשים בבגדי זהב מבחוץ, Aval d'varim hana'asim bevigdei
zahav mibachutz, things you wear the golden garments on the outside for,
which could be the תמיד, Tamid, it could be the מוסף, Musaf,
or specifically in terms of the special קרבנות Korbanot for יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, the איל. Ayil. Remember אהרן Aharon brings an איל, Ayil,
there's an איל Ayil for the people, but the פסוקים Psukim deal
with it in very short order, you know, ועשית את עולתך ואת
עולת העם. ve'asita olatecha ve'et olat ha'am. You know, so if you
did those things out of order, מה שעשה עשוי. ma she'asa asuy.
בדיעבד Bedi'eved it's okay. And an interesting thing to ask about רבי
נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia is what about the שעיר לעזאזל, Sa'ir LaAzazel, the
וידוי viduy of the שעיר לעזאזל? Sa'ir LaAzazel? That's בגדי לבן bigdei
lavan but it's not just, it's מבחוץ, mibachutz, it's out in the
עזרה. Azarah. Okay? So he, he
contracted בגדי לבן bigdei lavan בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ bein mifnim bein
mibachutz as opposed to בגדי זהב. bigdei zahav. But it seems that
the word מבחוץ, mibachutz, right, includes, includes the עזרה, Azarah, because he
says בגדי זהב בחוץ. bigdei zahav bachutz. Yes? So בחוץ bachutz includes
the עזרה, Azarah, because that's the בגדי זהב. bigdei zahav. So it
would seem according to him that the שעיר לעזאזל Sa'ir LaAzazel also
is part of the סדר. Seder. Anything in the white בגדים begadim
wherever you are, whether it's this מבפנים, mifnim, whether it's this מבחוץ,
mibachutz, whether it's that מבחוץ, mibachutz, which would be the שעיר לעזאזל,
Sa'ir LaAzazel, all of those things, those really special יום כיפור Yom
Kippur things, that's where סדר Seder is מעכב. me'akeiv. But anything you're
doing with בגדי זהב, bigdei zahav, there סדר Seder is not מעכב.
me'akeiv. Okay. Also as against the תמיד? Tamid?
Yeah, that's actually an interesting big תוספות Tosafot about that. In general,
whether the, whether the fact that the תמיד Tamid has to come
first makes פסול pasul you know, other things.
So even if he says
בדיעבד bedi'eved it could be later? No, no, but what would happen
בדיעבד? bedi'eved? Okay, so there's the
debate. אמר רבי יוחנן שניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Sheneihem
mikra echad darshu. They both learned it out from the same פסוק.
pasuk. Where do you get to say, a, that it's מעכב me'akeiv
and, b, that it's by one thing or the other thing? So
it says וזאת לכם לחקת עולם, Vezot lachem lechukat olam, this should
be for you for an eternal edict, אחת בשנה, achat bashanah, once
in a year. So the חוקה chukah means חוק, chok, order matters,
everything has to be exact, but the אחת, achat, right, seems to
say something unique. So the unique aspects, the things that are אחת
בשנה, achat bashanah, that's where it's a חוק, chok, right, the things
that are special. So what are the things that are special? רבי
יהודה סבר מקום שמתכפרין בו פעם אחת בשנה. Rabbi Yehuda savar Makom
shemitkaprin bo pa'am achat bashanah.
What is so special that this is only once in a year
is only once in a year do you do things inside the
קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Okay, so when it says this is a
חקת עולם chukat olam to be done only once a year, once
a year the תורה Torah is underscoring what's done in the קודש
קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, that's what's so special. And therefore there, if you
go out of order, it actually is a problem.
It's like you're saying everything
inside...
So the unique is either the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, I'll grant
you that, but what's also unique is other things are unique. The
use of בגדי זהב, bigdei zahav, of בגדי לבן, bigdei lavan, so
anything that's done with בגדי לבן bigdei lavan is what is אחת
בשנה, achat bashana, what is unique, and that's where order matters. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says אטו atu one minute, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda מקום כתיב? makom ketiv? I don't get it. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says once, once means the one special place. It doesn't
say place, it says once. We should focus on everything that's unique,
which is everything that's done with the בגדי לבן. bigdei lavan. So
how does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda limit it to what's done in
the קודש קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim? אלא היינו טעמא דרבי יהודה. ela haynu
ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda.
This is the reasoning of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. כתיב זאת. ketiv
zot. It says והייתה זאת לכם לחוקת עולם ve'hayta zot lachem lechukat
olam וכתיב אחת. ve'ketiv achat. So again remember זאת zot is limiting,
only this, not more. So the extra זאת zot makes it constricted
even more. אחת achat I would have said like you, everything בגדי
לבן. bigdei lavan. Okay, that's what's unique, but זאת zot makes it
constricted even more and limits you to the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
חד למיעוטי בגדי לבן מבחוץ וחד למיעוטי בגדי זהב. chad lemi'utei bigdei
lavan mibachutz vechad lemi'utei bigdei zahav. So one of them is to
say, well, the order should have been different. The first thing you
exclude from the חוק chok is the בגדי זהב bigdei zahav and
then you have a זאת, zot, right? Because that I would have
agreed, fine, everything unique, everything in the white בגדים. begadim. But then
the זאת zot comes and that says no, even that
is a smaller category, only things that are super special, only the
stuff that's done in the
קודש קודשים.
Kodesh Kodashim.
אין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא
לרבות.
ein mi'ut achar mi'ut
ela lerebot. Yeah, except when we want to. רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya,
רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya says חד למיעוטי בגדי זהב וחד למיעוטי שיריים
דלא מעכבי. chad lemi'utei bigdei zahav vechad lemi'utei shirayim delo me'akvei. I
concede that there are two words, but I, one of them says
this חוק chok is only by the things that are special, בגדי
לבן. bigdei lavan. If I have another word זאת, zot, I'm not
going to make that בגדי לבן bigdei lavan a smaller category. That's
special, everything there order matters. So what will זאת zot exclude? זאת
zot will exclude one עבודה avoda done by the בגדי לבן bigdei
lavan that there order does not matter, and which is the עבודה?
avoda? שיריים. shirayim. The pour of the שיריים shirayim of the blood
here at the base of the מזבח. mizbeach. There, and if you
went out of order with that, that is not going to be
מעכב me'akev because in general the assumption is that שיריים shirayim is
not an essential part of the כפרה. kapara.
You do it a lot later, it could have been earlier, otherwise
it would be שיריים, shirayim, right? What? I'm sorry? Mean when did
you do it?
Means if you went ahead and you did, let's say you did
the וידוי vidui of the שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la'azazel before the שיריים.
shirayim. So the fact that you bumped the שיריים shirayim out of
order does not prevent you, the fact that you did the שיריים
shirayim later does not prevent something else from being valid. Okay,
fine. By the way, just to confuse you, I'm concerned whether I'll
mention this, but anyway, but what's not clear is we say if
it's only by בגדי לבן bigdei lavan or בגדי לבן בפנים bigdei
lavan bifnim that order matters, what if one of the things is
from the category that order matters and one thing is from the
category that order doesn't matter? You know what I mean? Let's say
you do the איל העם ayil ha'am and you interrupt one of
the things in בגדי לבן. bigdei lavan. Is that okay? Doesn't matter
because that was just the איל. ayil. That's not a בגדי לבן
bigdei lavan thing. Or does it matter because it interrupted the בגדי
לבן? bigdei lavan? Okay, it sounds here like what defines, or you
can have the reverse. You went out, you know, you started the
קטורת ketoret too early, you know, in the process of things that
were being done בבגדי זהב. bevigdei zahav. You know? So which determines
the stuff that's being interrupted or the interrupt or the interruptor? It
sounds like what determines is the interruptee, because it's saying here you
haven't done the שיריים, shirayim, you interrupted it with something, not a
problem, it's only the שיריים. shirayim. Okay, so but normally what defines
the problem is that you've interrupted things that are בבגדי לבן. bevigdei
lavan. Now I've totally confused you. Okay, anyway, the basic point is
that רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya says, רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya says everything
that's אחת בשנה achat bashana is special. Everything that's בגדי לבן bigdei
lavan is special. If you interrupt them, it's invalid. The one exception
is not to make that a smaller category but is to exclude
שיריים. shirayim. Since שיריים shirayim is not an essential part of כפרה,
kapara, if you interrupted שיריים, shirayim, you did something before שיריים, shirayim,
that does not invalidate the thing that you did. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say back, אי
מעכבי מעכבי ואי לא מעכבי לא מעכבי. ee me'akvei me'akvei ve'ee lo
me'akvei lo me'akvei. He would, it sounds like a tautology. He says
no, I don't agree with you. If you're going to say that
everything in בגדי לבן bigdei lavan is an issue, then it should
include שיריים. shirayim. And if you're going to say בגדי לבן bigdei
lavan like I say is not an issue outside of the קודש
קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, it doesn't include שיריים. shirayim. But basically it's a
way of saying I don't see any reason to single out שיריים.
shirayim. I see a reason to single out outside of the
קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. including outside of the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim,
I don't understand why you would make שירים Shiurayim any different.
Now the criterion is בגדי לבן. Bigdei Lavan.
Right, so then it should be it should be part of it,
בגדי לבן. Bigdei Lavan. Now of course that seems a little strange
because we can understand why it should be different. It should be
different because שירים Shiurayim is not essential to the כפרה. Kapparah. So
let's take, well I won't say that, so let's, I mean it's
שיירי כפרה, Sheyarei Kapparah, it's a piece of the כפרה Kapparah but
it's not essential. So the גמרא Gemara says כדתניא. Ki Detanya. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to help us
understand. Okay, וכלה
מכפר את הקודש. Vechilah Mekapper Et Hakodesh. He will finish atoning for
the קודש. Kodesh. So what does that mean? So what do we
learn from that? אם כפר כלה. Im Kipper Kilah. If you have
done your atonement, then you're done. ואם לא כפר לא כלה. Veim
Lo Kipper Lo Kilah. And if you didn't do your atonement, you're
not done. דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. That's what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says. You're not done till you're done. Okay? So when
you did the atonement, then you're done. אמר לו רבי יהודה. Amar
Lo Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said back to him,
מפני מה לא נאמר, Mipnei Mah Lo Nomar, why don't we say
the opposite? אם כלה כפר. Im Kilah Kipper. When you're done, that's
when you did your atonement. ואם לא כלה לא כפר. Veim Lo
Kilah Lo Kipper. If you didn't finish, you didn't do your atonement.
So what's the difference between those? One says once you've done the
atonement, you're done. And the other says no, once you're done, then
you've achieved the atonement. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so שאם חיסר אחת מן המתנות, Sheim Chissar Achat Min Hamattanot, because
if you say the emphasis is when you're done, when you're good
and done, that's when you've achieved the atonement, that means
לא עשה ולא כלום. Loasah Velo Klum. You haven't accomplished anything. If
you underscore when you're done, only when you're done, it means you
have to have done everything and only then you achieve your atonement.
ואמרינן Veamrinan and we say in another גמרא Gemara מאי בינייהו? Mai
Beinayhu? What difference does it make if you say when you're done
you atone or when you've atoned you're done? רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע
בן לוי. Rabbi Yochanan Verabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi. It's a debate of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua Ben
Levi. חד אמר Chad Amar משמעות דורשין איכא בינייהו. Mashmaut Dorshin Ika
Beinayhu. There's really no difference. It's just like, you know, how you
read the פסוק. Pasuk. But there's no practical difference of saying when
you're done you've atoned or when you've atoned you're done. They're basically
all saying the same thing. But it doesn't sound that way. So
וחד אמר, Vechad Amar, the other says no, if you say when
you're done, that's when it works, and therefore everything must be done.
And that's to tell you שירים מעכבי איכא בינייהו. Shiurayim Meakvei Ika
Beinayhu. That the difference is exactly this point of the שירים. Shiurayim.
That even though normally we say that שירים Shiurayim are לא מעכבי,
Lo Meakvei, if you don't pour the remnant blood at the base,
the קרבן Korban is still good, here the תורה Torah underscores וכלה.
Vechilah. Only when you've done everything, then are you have you atoned.
So here by, you know, by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, שירים Shiurayim
is מעכבי. Meakvei. Okay? So that would be the exact debate, would
be the debate. רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah says, I think the order
matters in everything in the בגדי לבן Bigdei Lavan but not by
the שירים, Shiurayim, because I even by יום כיפור Yom Kippur treat
the שירים Shiurayim as a lower category, as not as essential. And
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says back, you have no right to treat
the שירים Shiurayim as not essential. שירים Shiurayim by יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is מעכבי. Meakvei. And therefore it's going to be a problem,
and according to you, you should know, you have no basis for
excluding it from this concern of order. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi Amar Rabbi Yochanan Hachi?
Does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say this? Really say that this
is the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemiah whether and the issue of שירים מעכבי Shiurayim Meakvei is part
of their debate? והאמר רבי יוחנן, Veha Amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan himself says, תנא רבי נחמיה
כדברי האומר שירים מעכבי. Tana Rabbi Nechemiah Kedivrei Haomer Shiurayim Meakvei. That
our משנה, Mishna, a משנה Mishna in זבחים, Zevachim, I'll talk about
the משנה Mishna in a minute, but let's not worry about the
context there, but in זבחים, Zevachim, in a discussion over there, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah holds that שירים
Shiurayim is מעכבי. Meakvei. Okay? So if רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah himself
holds that שירים Shiurayim is מעכבי, Meakvei, how can he say that
by, that if you go out of order with the שירים, Shiurayim,
it doesn't matter? All right, now again, I don't know if I've
confused
you, so let me repeat it. Okay? So according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says this is the only thing
where order matters. Okay? Here's where order matters, only here. Okay? Comes
רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah and רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah says because this
is אחת בשנה, Achat Bashanah, the special place. Comes רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemiah and רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah says all of this
and probably the שעיר לעזאזל, Seir Leazazel, we'll put it in there
for a moment, because it's also בגדי לבן, Bigdei Lavan, since it's
also בגדי לבן. Bigdei Lavan. Okay, so but now where do they
get it? Because you're excluding two things. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
first excludes everything out here, בגדי זהב, Bigdei Zahav, and then he
excludes this and he's left with only here order matters. רבי נחמיה,
Rabbi Nechemiah, he excludes the בגדי זהב. Bigdei Zahav. What's the other
thing that רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah excludes? He excludes what we didn't
mention here, which is number nine, שירים, Shiurayim, right after you did
that. I don't know why we didn't put it in. That was
the next thing in the משנה *Mishna*, the pouring of the שריים
*shirayin*. So the one thing that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* excludes is
the pouring of the שריים *shirayin*. There, if you bumped something, if
you did one through eight and something else now interrupted that order,
it’s not a problem, all that was left is the שריים *shirayin*,
that’s not a problem for having gone out of order. Now, the
reason is presumably because שריים *shirayin* is not essential. Okay, but we’ve
got a problem and we just taught this whole ברייתא *braita*: אם
כילה כיפר כיפר כילה *im kila kiper kiper kila*, that according to
one way of reading the פסוקים *psukim*, you have to do everything
on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, and in which it would mean only
כילה *kila* is a כיפר *kiper*, means if on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* even the שריים *shirayin* is essential. That’s one reason, but maybe
רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* disagrees, שריים *shirayin* isn’t essential, so order doesn’t
matter here. But in the end, the גמרא *Gemara* was left with
a problem, because רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says over in another סוגיא
*sugya*
that רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* says שריים *shirayin* is essential, שריים *shirayin*
is מעכב *meakev*. So if רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* says שריים *shirayin*
is מעכב *meakev*, what he can’t be excluding, what is the other
thing he’s excluding? He’s excluding בגדי זהב *bigdei zahav*, but you can’t
be excluding שריים *shirayin* because you, רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* himself, holds
שריים *shirayin* is מעכב *meakev*. So that’s the גמרא *Gemara*’s problem, and
the גמרא *Gemara* just says and the גמרא *Gemara* just ends with
קשיא *kashya*. Alright, fine, this problem. But anyway, but basically what it
basically boils down to though is רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says here’s
where it’s מעכב *meakev*, and רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* says everything here,
maybe even including שילוח לעזאזל *shiluach l’Azazel*, is it מעכב *meakev*? Everything
that’s done בבגדי לבן *b’bigdei lavan*. How about שריים *shirayin*? Is שריים
*shirayin* part of that? Well actually, it’s a good thing you ask
because שריים *shirayin* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* is a debate whether
שריים *shirayin* is מעכב *meakev* in general, even if you didn’t do
it, meaning not on the rest of the year שריים *shirayin* is
not, but on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* because of אם כילה *im
kila*, it could be that שריים *shirayin* is מעכב *meakev*, and since
שריים *shirayin* is, and therefore would it also be an issue of
going out of order?
That depends on what you think about שריים *shirayin* on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*, whether or not it’s
מעכב
*meakev*. Okay, Dov, you had a question. According to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*, according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, what does כפרה *kapara* depend
upon? In יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, he was just saying that it’s
your כוונה *kavana*. No, no, no, but presumably it just means the
classic, if you say שריים איכא בינייהו *shirayin ika beiniyahu*, then he
just says אם כיפר כילה *im kiper
kila*, once you’ve done
the normal things that are essential to כפרה *kapara*, which is the
putting of the דם *dam* on the, you know, the sprinkling of
the blood, you know, then you’re done, even if you didn’t do
the שריים *shirayin*, where the other view is no, no, no, first
you got to do everything here. Really boils down to that. That’s
שריים איכא בינייהו *shirayin ika beiniyahu*. Right, שריים איכא בינייהו *shirayin ika
beiniyahu*. Now, I will in order just to tell you one sentence
about where רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* is, you know, where רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* says that רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* holds שריים *shirayin* is
מעכב *meakev*, it’s a big תוספות *Tosafot* because he tries to make
sense of it. It’s really, it’s not in the context of יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*. There’s a question about when you שחט *shacht* an
animal that’s קודש
*kodesh* outside of the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, you’re חייב *chayav* for שחוטי חוץ *shchutei chutz*, שוחט
קדשים *shochet kodshim* outside. Let’s say you burn the
limbs of an animal, you’re also חייב *chayav* on an
altar, you’re also חייב *chayav*. What if you do the ritual of
pouring שריים *shirayin* on a base of your own little private altar
outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*? Are you חייב *chayav* for an
עבודה בחוץ *avoda b’chutz*? Is the שריים *shirayin* doing, is that עבודה
בחוץ *avoda b’chutz*? If a כהן *kohen* left the בית, yeah, כהן
*kohen* or זר *zar*, whatever, a כלי *kli* of blood and שריים
*shirayin*, exactly, and he poured it out, right, and he, exactly, exactly.
Well no, but you’re obviously חייב *chayav* if you do זריקת הדם
בחוץ *zrikas hadam b’chutz*. Right, exactly. So רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* says
you’re חייב *chayav* for שפיכת שריים *shpichas shirayin*. And the גמרא *Gemara*
says, oh, and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, why, why would you
be חייב *chayav* for שפיכת שריים *shpichas shirayin*? I mean, it’s normally
not מעכב *meakev*, you know, so therefore it’s not an essential עבודה
*avoda*. Oh, this proves that according to רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah*, שריים
*shirayin* is מעכב *meakev*. Now that’s very problematic because that’s not talking
about יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. That sounds like רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah*
generally says שריים *shirayin* is מעכב *meakev*. So anyway, there’s a lot
of contradictory סוגיות *sugyos*. The basic upshot of it is, of this
long תוספות *Tosafot* says no, what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying
is that רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* would never give weight to שריים
*shirayin* during the rest of the year if there wasn’t one time
that שריים *shirayin* was מעכב *meakev*. Since on, there’s one time on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* שריים *shirayin* is מעכב *meakev*, that shows you
the weight of this issue of שפיכת שריים *shpichas
shirayin*, and that’s why he’s prepared to be מחייב *mechayev* you even
if you do it out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
There’s other things that are not מעכב *meakev* that you are חייב
*chayav* out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. The burning of the
limbs, the burning of the אימורים *imurim*, right, that’s not מעכב *meakev*
and you’re חייב *chayav* if you do it out of the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So the same is true according to רבי נחמיה
*Rabbi Nechemiah* by the שריים *shirayin*, but how do I know it
has that weight?
שריים *shirayin* seems to be a grade B עבודה *avoda*.
I know it has that weight because on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
it’s מעכב *meakev*. Okay, so
now we have been informed that all of this is מעכב *meakev*
if you don’t do it. שריים *shirayin* is an interesting debate, is
it מעכב *meakev* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? And then this question
of where does order matter? Here, or order matters everything in terms
of the בגדי לבן *b’bigdei lavan*. It might be the עצם היום
*etzem hayom* that’s giving it the weight, and not something intrinsic about
the שריים *shirayin* itself. Right, similar to the idea, it could be
the אחת בשנה *achas bashana* type of idea, and all of this
is only once in the year. Okay, let’s read a little bit
more, although we do have to end soon because it’s Tuesday. אמר
רבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi Chanina*, אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*. שחפנה
קודם שחיטת שור של פר לא עשה ולא כלום *shechafnah kodem shechitat
sor shel par lo asah velo klum*. Let's say you did the
scooping of the קטורת *ketoret* before you שחט *shecht*ed the פר *par*.
So where does that come in? So actually, the פר *par*'s all
in the beginning. Right? Right. So actually we skipped. We went straight
from the שחיטת פר *shechitat par* to the קטורת *ketoret*. But really
there's a 2a, which is חפינת הקטורת *chafinat haketoret*. Ah. And then
there's a 2b, which is the הקרבה *hakravah* of the קטורת *ketoret*.
So he says what happens if you do the חפינת הקטורת *chafinat
haketoret* before שחיטת הפר *shechitat hapar*? Okay? You get ready. So you
did that first. לא עשה ולא כלום *lo asah velo klum*. So
the גמרא *gemara* says כמאן דלא כרבי יהודה *keman dela k'rabbi Yehuda*.
That's not like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Because remember רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says it only matters in the קודש קדשים *kodesh kodashim*. Here
you only went out of order in the stuff outside the קודש
קדשים *kodesh kodashim*. Okay. דאי כרבי יהודה אמר כי כתיב חוקה בדברים
הנעשים בבגדי לבן ובפנים הוא דכתיב *dei k'rabbi Yehuda amar ki ksiva
chuka bidvarim hana'asim bigdei lavan uvifnim hu deksiv*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
says it only matters in here if you go out of order,
not out here. So the גמרא *gemara* says אפילו תימא רבי יהודה
*afilu teima Rabbi Yehuda* צורך פנים כפנים דמי *tzorech pnim k'pnim dami*.
Things that are done for this, also order matters. So where does
order matter therefore? On this as well, right? שחיטת חפינה שחיטת הפר
חפינה ושחיטת השעיר *shechitat chafina shechitat hapar chafina ushchitat hasair*. Right, all
of this, right, is done for the sake of this. So actually
order matters from one through five and all of this. So the
only debate really is this stuff. Okay? Yeah, you with me? But
since this is done for that, order matters. You know where else
order doesn't matter, which I didn't even have? By שחיטת הפר *shechitat
hapar*, we have the וידוי הפר *vidui hapar* and the וידוי *vidui*
and הגרלה *hagralah*. Right, all of those things, right? Now, it's interesting,
according to רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* those things would be מעכב *me'akev*
the order. Okay, but anyway, for him, the stuff you need to
get inside, in that is מעכב *me'akev*, this is what is not
מעכב *me'akev*. So we will pick up with that גמרא *gemara*.